export const quizData = [
  {
    question: "Who is the author of Ramayana?",
    options: [
      "Maharshi Valmiki",
      "Maharshi Vyasa",
      "Maharshi Agasthi",
      "Narad Muni",
    ],
    answer: "Maharshi Valmiki",
    explanation:
      "Maharshi Valmiki is the author of Ramayana. He is considered to be the original author of the epic Hindu scripture, which narrates the story of Lord Rama.",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the king of Kishkindha?",
    options: ["Sugriv", "Neel", "Hanuman", "Nal"],
    answer: "Sugriv",
    explanation:
      "Sugriv is the correct answer because he was the king of Kishkindha according to the Hindu epic Ramayana.",
  },
  {
    question: "Rama is the Avatar of",
    options: ["Shiv", "Vishnu", "Brahma", "Brahmin"],
    answer: "Vishnu",
    explanation:
      "Rama is considered to be the avatar or incarnation of Vishnu, who is also known as Narayana.",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who of the following was turned into a human being from stone upon Rama's touch?",
    options: ["Ahalya", "Devayani", "Savitri", "Anasuya"],
    answer: "Ahalya",
    explanation:
      "Ahalya was turned into a human being from stone upon Rama's touch. This incident is mentioned in Hindu mythology, specifically in the Ramayana.",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following dynasty does Rama belong to?",
    options: ["Chandrahasa", "Kritarta", "Ikshvaku", "Raghuvamsa"],
    answer: "Ikshvaku",
    explanation:
      "Rama belongs to the Ikshvaku dynasty. This is evident from various Hindu scriptures and epics, such as the Ramayana.",
  },
  {
    question: "Who of the following are brothers?",
    options: [
      "Hanuman and Angada",
      "Vibhishana and Jambhavantha",
      "Vali and Sugreeva",
      "Vali and Ravana",
    ],
    answer: "Vali and Sugreeva",
    explanation:
      "Vali and Sugreeva are brothers because they both belong to the same Vanara clan in the Hindu epic Ramayana.",
  },
  {
    question: "When Rama broke the bow of Lord Shiva, which sage was angered?",
    options: ["Vasishta", "Dhoorvasa", "Bhrugu", "Parshuram"],
    answer: "Parshuram",
    explanation:
      "When Rama broke the bow of Lord Shiva, it angered Parshuram. Parshuram, an avatar of Lord Vishnu, was known for his fierce temper.",
  },
  {
    question: "Lord Rama belonged to which Yug",
    options: ["Kaliyug", "Tretayug", "DwaparYug", "SatyaYug"],
    answer: "Tretayug",
    explanation:
      "Lord Rama is a central figure in the Hindu epic Ramayana, and his stories are believed to have taken place during Tretayug",
  },
  {
    question: "Which bird was Jatayu?",
    options: ["Eagle", "Vulture", "Penguin", "Crow"],
    answer: "Vulture",
    explanation:
      "Jatayu was a bird in Indian mythology who played a significant role in the epic Ramayana. He was a vulture.",
  },
  {
    question: "Ayodhya was the capital of which Kingdom?",
    options: ["Mithila", "Indraprastha", "Kosala", "Lanka"],
    answer: "Kosala",
    explanation:
      "Ayodhya, also known as Saket, is an ancient city of India and used to be the capital of the ancient Kosala Kingdom.",
  },
];
